Guide to the Gil J Wolman Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Lettrist Movement Material, 1946-1992; 1952-1964; Series II; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  Series II. documents the evolution of Lettrism in France in the 1950s and 1960s through original texts, publications, ephemera, and internal documents collected by Wolman. The series comprises Lettrist poems, screenplays, and theoretical texts in manuscript or typescript authored by the movement's leading figures, and sometimes annotated by other group members. Including writings by Guy Debord, Jean Louis Brau, Serge Berna, François Dufrêne, Isidore Isou, and others, the series illustrates a period of collaboration amongst figures who would later disassociate. Of note is the unpublished last pages of Guy Debord's "Manifeste pour une construction des situations," dated 1953 September 21, and long thought to be lost.
  The series also contains literary and theoretical magazines, including a complete run of the Internationale lettriste's newsletter Potlatch (1954-1959); tracts and other printed ephemera; and internal documents like account books and notes regarding the publication of Lettrist magazines. Beyond Lettrist material, the series also includes a few publications from related avant-garde groups such as the Internationale situationniste and the Mouvement international pour un Bauhaus imaginiste.
  For writings by Wolman on mégapneumie, "art integral," Debord's developing situationist theories, and other early Lettrist notes, see Series III. Writings, Subseries. Early Lettrist Writings. For screenplay drafts of Wolman's Lettrist film L'Anticoncept, see Series IV., Box 38, Folders 522-531.
  Organized into three subseries: Collected Writings, Publication and Ephemera, and Internal Documents.
  - Collected Writings
    Arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Berna, Serge
      - "Les jeux de l'amour et du hasard: Fragments d'un roman-film influentiel", screenplay, autograph manuscript with pasted images, 1952- (Box 6, Folder 139)
      - "Jusqu'à l'os", printed text with manuscript corrections, circa 1952 (Box 6, Folder 140)
        See also: Series IV. Box 38, Folder 530-531, for printing proofs of the magazine Ion, no. 1 (1952), in which Berna's text was published along with Wolman's script for L'Anticoncept.
    - Bertini, Gianni. "Conversation avec Giulio Carlo Argan", typescript with manuscript corrections, 1977-12-04- (Box 6, Folder 141)
    - Brau, Jean Louis, François Dufrêne, and Gil J Wolman. "Limelight", tract, typescript, 1964- (Box 6, Folder 142)
    - Brau, Jean Louis
      - ["La citadelle"], screenplay, typescript, circa 1952 (Box 6, Folder 143)
      - "Halte au clown", tract, typescript, 1963-06-15- (Box 6, Folder 144)
      - "La méthode Romi" / "Étude de structure", typescript, circa 1962 (Box 6, Folder 145)
      - "Le point final d'une ténébreuse affaire", typescript, 1962-10-18- (Box 6, Folder 146)
        Accompanied by "Annexe I: Sur ma qualité de lettriste, sur mon inconditionalité et ses limites," typescript.
      - "Ptotel'asymptotel'asymptotel", placard published by the Groupe d'études et de recherches méta-esthétiques, 1959-01 (Box 56 (Oversize), Folder 736)
    - Cahiers pour un dictat artistique. Statement on the arrest of Serge Berna, typescript, [1950] (Box 6, Folder 147)
      Back of sheet features an autograph note from Jean Louis Brau. Accompanied by a letter from C.P. Matricon to Jean Louis Brau (dated 18 November 1950) expressing disagreement with the Cahiers pour un dictat artistique's statement.
    - Cathelin, Jean. "Thrène pour M.L., cadavre vivant à conspuer éminement en forme de sonnet", typescript, 1963- (Box 6, Folder 148)
    - Debord, Guy
      - Internationale lettriste, drafts for issue no. 3, [1953] (Box 6, Folder 149)
        Drafts, typescript with manuscript corrections by Guy Debord, for texts to be published in issue no. 3.
      - "Manifeste pour une construction de situations", last six pages, typescript with autograph corrections, 1953-09-21- (Box 6, Folder 150-152)
        Continuation of the "Manifeste pour une construction de situations," posthumously published in incomplete form in Oeuvres (Gallimard, 2006). Accompanied by Lettrist tracts and poems by Debord and others: Jean Louis Brau, "La corrida chez le prophète" (undated); Debord, "Scandaleux droit de survivre", and "Prochaine planète" (undated); Internationale Lettriste, ["L'indifférence a fait ce monde"] (1954 May 05); Gilles Ivain, ["L'activité principale...dérive continue"] (1953 October 03); Jean-Michel Mension, "Lock-out" (undated); Jean Rollin, "Vers un baptême lettriste" (circa 1963); Unknown, "36 Rue des Morillons" and "Rythme farouche" (undated).
    - Deuxième internationale lettriste
      - "Examen de la pureté", tract, typescript with pasted cartoons, [1964] (Box 6, Folder 153)
      - "Isou nous deplaît" / "Lochhmar" tract, typescript, corrected, circa 1963 (Box 6, Folder 154)
    - Dufrêne, François
      - "Le lettrisme est toujours pendant", in Opus international issue no. 40-41, photocopy, [1973] (Box 6, Folder 155)
      - "Pragmatique du crirythme", placard, 1965-09 (Box 60 (Oversize), Folder 766)
      - "Tambours du jugement premier", screenplay, photocopy with manuscript annotations, 1973- (Box 6, Folder 156)
        Annotated for the 1973 recording at the Atelier de création radiophonique on France Culture, with the voices of Dufrêne, Wolman, and Jacques Spacagna.
      - "Texticules pour l'os à moelle" / "Discours de Monsieur Savoskesavo au Congrès du Plan de Polarisation", autograph manuscripts, undated (Box 6, Folder 157)
    - [Gros, Louis]. Lettrist poems, typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 158)
    - Isou, Isidore
      - Annotations to the exhibit flyer for La lettre et le signe dans la peinture contemporaine, 1963- (Box 6, Folder 159)
      - "Assez de plagieurs du lettrisme et de l'art supertemporel", tract, typescript with autograph corrections, undated (Box 6, Folder 160)
      - "Contre la confusion dans la poésie phonétique", tract, typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 161)
      - "Contre l'Internationale (sic) lettriste", confusionniste et scissionniste, [...]", tract, typescript with autograph corrections, undated (Box 6, Folder 162)
        Accompanied by the tract "Nouvelles explications sur les scissionnistes réactionnaires de l'"Internationale" (sic)", typescript with autograph corrections.
      - "La dernière infamie de Maurice Lemaître", tract, typescript with autograph corrections, circa 1962 (Box 6, Folder 163)
      - "Lemaître corrompt mes amis", tract, typescript with autograph corrections, [1962] (Box 6, Folder 164)
        Accompanied by a typed circular letter by Jean Cathelin, dated 1962 August 09, responding to Isou's text.
      - Le lettrisme et l'hypergraphie dans la peinture et la sculpture contemporaines, partial proofs with corrections, circa 1961 (Box 6, Folder 165)
      - "Manifeste de l'anti-meca-esthétique", drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript, circa 1962 (Box 7, Folder 166)
        Manifesto authored jointly by Isou, Wolman, Gabriel Pomerand, and Jacques Spacagna.
      - "Les moyens de réalisation dans l'art plastique lettriste et infinitésimal (la méca-esthétique et le cadre supertemporel)", printed article with illustrations, 1972 (Box 56 (Oversize), Folder 737)
      - "Proposition de plan d'activités des lettristes pour l'année 1963-64", memorandum, typescript (Box 7, Folder 167)
      - Tract against the Ministère de la Justice's laws on erotic literature, autograph manuscript, circa 1960 (Box 7, Folder 168)
      - Traité de bave et d'éternité, partial screenplay draft, autograph manuscript, circa 1951 (Box 7, Folder 169)
      - Traité de bave et d'éternité, screenplay, typescript, circa 1951 (Box 7, Folder 170)
      - Traité de bave et d'éternité, recording notes, circa 1951 (Box 61 (Oversize), Folder 774)
      - [Isou, Isidore]. Untitled screenplay, autograph manuscript and typescript, undated (Box 7, Folder 171-172)
        Manuscript in the hand of Isidore Isou and typescript with additions by Wolman for an untitled sound or film script.
        - Fragile originals (Box 66, Folder 802-803)
    - Lemaître, Maurice. "Manifeste du créatisme", typescript, 1966-02-25- (Box 7, Folder 173)
    - Straram, Patrick. ["Préface, qu'on comprenne…"], typescript with manuscript corrections, undated (Box 7, Folder 174)
    - Szpiro, Maurice-Alain. "La veste", short story, typescript with manuscript corrections, circa 1955 (Box 7, Folder 175)
      Vendor inventory identifies Szpiro as a friend of Jean Louis Brau.
    - Villeglé. "De Mathieu à Mahé", typescript, after 1965 (Box 7, Folder 176)
    - Unknown. ["Erratum: dans le livre de la connaissance…"], typescript, circa 1960 (Box 7, Folder 177)
    - Unknown. ["Que tout signe se cripse aussitôt écrit…"], typescript, undated (Box 7, Folder 178)
  - Publications and Ephemera
    Arranged alphabetically by creator, or by title.
    - A magazine, undated (Box 7, Folder 179-180)
      Numbered copy with original artwork, as well as preparatory material.
    - Apeïros, XXI. Internationale Buch-Ausstellung issue, 1972-11- (Box 7, Folder 181)
    - Arguments lettristes, no. 1, [1964] (Box 7, Folder 182)
    - "Au Tabou, 4 recitals lettristes" poster, 1950 (Box 62 (Oversize), Folder 782)
    - Avant-garde lettriste et esthapeïriste, no. 1-2, 1964- (Box 7, Folder 183-184)
    - Belgian Surrealism file, 1952-1966 (Box 7, Folder 185)
      Original grouping of flyers, booklets, tracts, and clippings relating to René Magritte, Jane Graverol, Roger van de Wouwer, and Mirabelle Dors.
    - Bref no. 64, "La poésie lettriste - récital au T.N.P.", 1963-03 (Box 56 (Oversize), Folder 738)
    - Comité psychogéographique de Londres. "Le communiqué de Begnins", 1989-10-01- (Box 7, Folder 186)
    - Deuxième internationale lettriste, after 1963 (Box 7, Folder 187)
    - La dictature lettriste, cahier no. 1, [1956] (Box 7, Folder 188)
    - "En marge": La revue du refus pour une nouvelle participation, [1955] (Box 7, Folder 189-190)
      Two copies, one incomplete.
    - Front de la jeunesse, issue no. 1, [1950] (Box 7, Folder 191)
      Contains three copies of the issue, including one with ownership signature by Tristan Tzara. Substitutes have been provided for two copies in fragile condition.
      - Fragile originals (Box 66, Folder 804)
    - Gruppe Spur. Printed manifesto, [1958?] (Box 7, Folder 192)
    - Internationale lettriste
      - "Documents" booklet, circa 1955 (Box 7, Folder 193)
      - Internationale lettriste, issue no. 2, [1953] (Box 7, Folder 194)
        Three copies and a paste-up with manuscript corrections.
      - Internationale lettriste, issue [no.3] with proofs, [1953] (Box 56 (Oversize), Folder 739)
      - Potlatch newsletter, 1954-1959 (Box 8, Folder 195-200)
        Contains issues no.1-29 (1954-1957), and issue no.1 (1959) of the new series. No. 1-28 are issued in the name of the Internationale lettriste group, while no. 29 and no. 1 (new series) are issued by the Internationale situationniste group.
      - Printed advertisements, circa 1955 (Box 8, Folder 201)
      - Printed statements, circa 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 202)
        Contains "Finis les pieds plats", "Touchez pas aux lettristes", "Deutschland über alles", and "Ordre de boycott" for the the Festival de la Cité Radieuse.
      - "Toutes ces dames au salon" placard, circa 1956 (Box 60 (Oversize), Folder 767)
        Issued jointly with Les lèvres nues.
    - Internationale situationniste
      - "Déclaration sur les procès contre l'Internationale Situationniste en Allemagne Fédérale", 1962-06-25- (Box 8, Folder 203)
      - Flyers and declarations, 1962-1964 (Box 8, Folder 204)
        Includes the tracts "Au secours de Van Guglielmi!" by Asger Jorn (1958), "Sur l'exclusion d'Attila Kotànyi" (1963), and an address to the Assemblée générale de l'Association internationale des critiques d'art (1958).
      - Oversize declaration and posters, 1962-1963 (Box 61 (Oversize), Folder 775)
        Contains the declaration "Pas de dialogue avec les suspects, pas de dialogues avec les cons" (1963), a poster paste-up for the sixth Internationale Situationniste congress (1962), and the poster "Nouveau théâtre d'opérations dans la culture" (undated).
    - Internationale situationniste II. Bauhaus situationiste brochure, 1989-03- (Box 8, Folder 205)
      Transcription of speeches given by Jörgen Nash and Jean Sellem at the Centre Georges Pompidou, 1989 February 21.
    - Isou, Isidore, clippings file, 1946-1952 (Box 8, Folder 206)
      Folder of clippings about Isou collected by Wolman, all but three regarding the critical reception of Traité de bave et d'éternité. Accompanied by a photographic print of Alexandre Serge Stavisky.
      - Oversize clipping, undated (Box 56 (Oversize), Folder 740)
      - Fragile original clippings (Box 66, Folder 805)
    - Jorn, Asger
      - Contre le fonctionnalisme pamphlet, circa 1961 (Box 8, Folder 207)
      - De la méthode triolectique dans ses applications en situologie générale pamphlet, 1964- (Box 8, Folder 208)
    - Lettrist cinema flyers, circa 1953 (Box 8, Folder 209)
      Includes "Fini le cinéma français", "Les Amis du Cinéma" flyers signed by members of the Lettrist group, and "La Nuit du Cinéma".
    - Lettrist file "Tract lettristes (Isou)", 1950-1973 (Box 8, Folder 210-212)
      Original grouping of material related to Lettrism [not solely to Isou], mostly dating from the later period in the 1960s-1970s. Includes flyers for exhibitions, recitals, and publications; internal documents; tracts and declarations.
      - Oversize exhibition poster "Les peintres lettristes - l'école du signe de 1946 en 1961" (Galerie Weiller) (Box 60 (Oversize), Folder 768)
    - Les lèvres nues
      - Advertisements "Apprenez à lire sur les lèvres nues", undated (Box 56 (Oversize), Folder 741)
      - Issue no. 9, 1959-11- (Box 8, Folder 213)
      - Placard for issue no. 2 "Ce qu'on appelle la tragédie antique", 1954-05-18 (Box 56 (Oversize), Folder 742)
    - Mouvement international pour un Bauhaus imaginiste. "C'est la lutte finale" tract., 1956- (Box 8, Folder 214)
    - Nouvelles génération, no. 1-2, 1962- (Box 8, Folder 215)
    - Ô magazine, no. F bis, circa 1966 (Box 8, Folder 216)
    - Paris Théâtre, no. 218, circa 1964 (Box 8, Folder 217)
      Editor-in-chief Maurice Lemaître.
    - La poésie et la musique lettristes et aphonistes event program, 1964- (Box 8, Folder 218)
    - Poésie nouvelle, supplements, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 219-220)
      Contains first and second supplements to no. 18 and no. 20, and second supplements only to no. 17 and no. 19.
    - Le port-folio situationniste volume 1, unbound photocopies, 1992- (Box 9, Folder 221)
    - Primo congresso mondiale degli artisti liberi ephemera, 1956-09- (Box 9, Folder 222)
    - La revue de psychokladologie et de psychothéie, no. 2, 1970-11- (Box 9, Folder 223)
    - Spacagna, Jacques. Je crie propre, journal hypergraphique poster, [1971] (Box 61 (Oversize), Folder 776)
    - "Tract-art" no. 3 special issue, 1976- (Box 9, Folder 224)
    - Transit, hors série issue, 1949- (Box 9, Folder 225)
      Features several poems by Jean Louis Brau
    - Ur: La dictature lettriste no. 2, circa 1952 (Box 9, Folder 226)
  - Internal Documents
    - Cinémathèque française, delivery sheet for the film Traité de bave et d'éternité, 1952-12-04- (Box 9, Folder 227)
    - Lettrist magazine publication accounts, circa 1952 (Box 9, Folder 228)
    - Miscellaneous file, undated (Box 9, Folder 229)
      Original grouping of documents, found in a folder labeled "Divers + planches photos Ion ", including notes in Wolman's hand and photographic prints of Béla Bartók.
    - Miscellaneous file, undated (Box 9, Folder 230)
      Original grouping of documents, found in a folder labeled "Documents sur la création de l'Internationale lettriste + Potlach + écrits", including a typed Lettrist poem, two drawings, and a photograph.
    - Ur: La dictature lettriste receipt book, 1952-03- (Box 9, Folder 231)
      Documenting the deposit of Ur copies in local bookstores.
    - Ur: La dictature lettriste documents, 1963-1964 (Box 9, Folder 232)
      Contains three circular letters regarding the publication of no. 1-2 of the new series of Ur signed by Roberto Altmann and Roland Sabatier, as well as two flyers and a printed cover design.
- Writings, 1950-1995; Series III; 12.69; (27 boxes)
  Series III. documents Wolman's literary works, from the theoretical writings about mégapneumie of his early Lettrist years, to his production of books from the late 1970s to the early 1990s. The bulk of the series consists of drafts, background material, visuals, and printing tests for Wolman's anthology Wolman résumé des chapitres précédents (1981), his artists' books, such as Dühring, Dühring (1979), and his poetic texts, especially Les inhumations: suivi de Peinture dépeinte (1995). Other writings include poems, theoretical notes relating to Lettrism, notations for mégapneumes, and unidentified manuscripts.
  Organized into four subseries: Books, Short Works, Early Lettrist Writings, and Notes and Untitled Manuscripts.
  For L'Anticoncept screenplay, see Series IV.
  - Books, 1960-1995
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    The subseries evidences Wolman's process for constructing books. Wolman's bookmaking intersected with his visual arts practices, particularly that of détournement through textual appropriation and photocopy art. Wolman utilized newspaper clippings, drawings, and appropriated or original texts and photographs, combined through collage and photocopy. For example, Dühring Dühring ([Paris]: Éditions inconnues, 1979) consists of nouns selected from Friedrich Engels's book Anti-Dühring placed atop drawings and photographs of human faces. Several books, such as L'homme séparé (1979), Dühring Dühring (1979), Haute vie (1987), were elaborated concurrently with a gallery installation featuring enlarged prints from the book's content.
    In addition to drafts and proofs, the subseries also contains reference materials gathered by Wolman in preparation for his retrospective book Wolman résumé des chapitres précédants (1981), and for a prospective sequel, organized in chronological folders. These largely include ephemera from exhibitions and festivals, and newspaper clippings.
    - De l'anticoncept à l'anticoncept, suivi de Les Inhumations, draft, autograph manuscript, circa 1990 (Box 10, Folder 233)
    - Appel à témoins, printed prototype under initial title Donner à dire, 1991-09-07- (Box 10, Folder 234)
    - Dühring Dühring
      - Background material, 1946- (Box 10, Folder 235)
        Three pages from Friedrich Engels's Anti-Dürhing.
      - Draft with corrections, autograph manuscript, 1976-10-02- (Box 10, Folder 236-246)
        On 5"x7" notecards, paginated on the verso.
      - Final drafts, typescript, 1976-10-02- (Box 11, Folder 247-250)
      - Copy under the alternate title Rencontre fortuite, typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 251)
      - Preparatory work for portraits and drawings, photocopies, [1979] (Box 11, Folder 252-253)
      - Published copy, signed, [1979] (Box 57 (Oversize), Folder 743)
    - Les entrepôts d'Ivry
      - Drafts, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 11, Folder 254)
      - Drafts, typescript with autograph corrections, undated (Box 11, Folder 255-256)
      - Newspaper and magazine clippings, undated (Box 11, Folder 257)
      - Photocopy cutouts, undated (Box 11, Folder 258)
      - Image paste-up and photocopies, undated (Box 12, Folder 259-260)
      - Unbound copy, [1986] (Box 12, Folder 261)
    - Fin de communication
      Initial title: Le monde du 22 novembre.
      - Le Monde annotated newspaper issue, 1974-11-22 (Box 61 (Oversize), Folder 777)
      - Notecards titled "Le monde du 22 novembre", autograph, undated (Box 12, Folder 262-266)
      - Notebooks titled "Des phrases déchirées dans le monde du 22 novembre", autograph, undated (Box 12, Folder 267-269)
      - Drafts titled "Communication", autograph manuscript and typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 270)
      - Drafts titled "Communication", typescript with autograph corrections, undated (Box 13, Folder 271)
      - Final drafts under the title "Le monde du 22 novembre", typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 272-275)
        Four copies
      - Text in layout frames, undated (Box 13, Folder 276)
      - Maquette of text frames painted in gouache, undated (Box 13, Folder 277)
      - Paste-up, typed text glued on photocopied frames, undated (Box 14, Folder 278)
      - Printing tests and copies file, undated (Box 14, Folder 279-280)
      - Spiral-bound copy, typescript with autograph corrections, [1977?] (Box 14, Folder 281)
        Pages 1-17 missing. Accompanied by an acknowledgement of receipt from Éditions du Seuil, dated 1977 May 03.
    - Haute vie
      - Photographic prints reproduced in the book, 1987-07- (Box 14, Folder 282)
      - Photocopies of enlarged photographs, [1987] (Box 14, Folder 283-284)
      - Photocopies of enlarged photographs, [1987] (Box 57 (Oversize), Folder 744)
      - Unbound book, [1987] (Box 14, Folder 285)
    - L'homme penché
      - Draft fragments, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 15, Folder 286-288)
        Untitled drafts relating to L'homme penché or L'homme séparé.
      - Draft, autograph manuscript, 1976- (Box 15, Folder 289-290)
        On 4"x6" notecards.
      - Maquette, photocopy of autograph manuscript, 1976- (Box 15, Folder 291)
    - L'homme séparé
      - Draft, typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 292)
        Accompanied by autograph drafts possibly related to L'homme séparé, including a dialogue ["L'homme est étendu sur la plage…"].
      - Cover designs, undated (Box 15, Folder 293)
      - Maquette, undated (Box 15, Folder 294-295)
        Text written in gouache in large characters on white pages torn in the middle and glued on black cardboard, paginated on the verso.
      - Unbound copies, [1979] (Box 16, Folder 296-298)
        Reproductions of the maquette on beige cardboard.
      - Copy torn in half, undated (Box 16, Folder 299)
      - Text on tracing paper and cardboard, undated (Box 17, Folder 300-309)
      - Text on tracing paper ("déchets"), undated (Box 18, Folder 310)
    - Les inhumations
      - Printed text with autograph dedication to Charlotte Wolman, undated (Box 19, Folder 311)
      - Printouts, undated (Box 19, Folder 312)
      - Printout of excerpt, undated (Box 19, Folder 313)
    - Journal jusqu'à l'exclusion
      - Typescript, [1988] (Box 19, Folder 314)
      - Series of fifteen postcards, undated (Box 19, Folder 315)
    - Le livre des mots
      - Maquette, 1987- (Box 19, Folder 316)
      - Printed copy in five volumes, 1987- (Box 19, Folder 317)
    - Des mots rayés nuls, uncut proof with corrections, 1993- (Box 19, Folder 318)
    - Le passage, maquette, [1989] (Box 19, Folder 319)
    - Peinture dépeinte
      As published by Éditions Allia (Paris: 1995) jointly with Les inhumations, Peinture dépeinte contains short poetic reflections recorded almost daily, dated from 1991 February 18 to 1994 October 11.The texts were also exhibited at the Galerie de Paris in 1994.
      - Drafts, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 20, Folder 320-326)
      - Drafts titled "14 Sept. 1991", autograph manuscript (Box 21, Folder 327-334)
      - Drafts titled "Peinture dépeinte journal, février 91", autograph manuscript, 1991- (Box 21, Folder 335-338)
      - Drafts, autograph manuscript, [1994] (Box 22, Folder 339-342)
      - Drafts, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 22, Folder 343)
      - Drafts, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 22, Folder 344-346)
      - Drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript, undated (Box 23, Folder 347-348)